Finding Aid for Kasimir Fajans Papers 1912-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kasimir Fajans Papers 1912-1987, 1936-1975
Fajans, Kasimir, 1887-
2 oversize items AC
14.5 linear feet
Professor of Chemistry at the University of Michigan, 1936-1957, previously professor at the University of Munich, internationally known for his work on radioactivity; papers include extensive correspondence files, lectures and publications, personal/biographical material and photographs.
85327 Aa/2, Ac
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Fajans, and came to the library in the period of 1975-1980. Additional materials have been received since that time. Donor no. 5728.
The collection is open for research.
Born in Warsaw, Poland, in 1887, Fajans was educated in Germany and received a Ph. D from the University of Heidelberg in 1909. He did postdoctoral studies with Richard Willstater at Zurich University and with Ernest Rutherford in Manchester, England. In 1911 he joined the staff of Karlsruhe Institute of Technology. From 1917 to 1935 he was a professor at the University of Munich, serving as the Director of the Institute of Physical Chemistry from 1932 to 1935. He was also director of the Institute for Physico-Chemical Measurements.
Before coming to the University of Michigan in 1936, Fajans had established an international reputation for his scientific achievements in many fields of both chemistry and physics. He was already an authority on many phases of radioactivity, refractivity, adsorption, molecular structure, crystal structure, photochemistry, and thermochemistry. In the early days of his studies in radioactivity, while working at Manchester, Karlsruhe, and Munich, Fajans was one of the first to develop the idea of matter as composed of isotopes of the several elements, and to make clear the nature of the transformation in the natural radioactive series. Fajans' studies on radioactivity established the radioactive displacement laws (Fajans-Soddy Displacement Laws) and helped place radio elements in the periodic system. The Fajans-Paneth-Hahn rule resulted from his work on the precipitation and absorption of radio elements and dye-ions. With Oswald Göhring, he discovered the Uranium x2 form of protactinium-234. His quanticule theory of chemical binding was the focus of his later work. Fajans retired from the university in 1957. He died in 1975.
The collection has been divided into six series: Correspondence, Lectures and symposia; Topical Files; Publications; Biographical/personal and Photographs.
The papers of Kasimir Fajans, professor of chemistry at the University of Michigan from 1936 to 1957, cover his career as a physical chemist dating from 1912 to 1975.
Subjects:
Chemistry.; Fajans, Kasimir, 1887-1975.; Refugees, Jewish.; Scientists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Universität München.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Chemistry.; Fajans family.; Fajans, Kasimir, 1887-1975.; Laboratories--Germany.; Offices.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Universität München.
Contributors:
Bernstein, Richard B. (Richard Barry), 1923-1990; Bodenstein, Max, 1871-1942.; Born, Max, 1882-1970.; Bragg, William Henry, Sir, 1862-1942.; Bredig, Georg, b. 1868.; Bridgman, P. W. (Percy Williams), 1882-1961.; Cady, George H., 1906-; Conant, James Bryant, 1893-1978.; Debye, Peter J. W. (Peter Josef William), 1884-1966; Engler, Karl, 1842-1925.; Euler, Hans von, 1873-1964.; Ewald, Paul Peter, 1888-1985; Fiekers, Bernard A., 1906-1973.; Foote, Paul D. (Paul Darwin), 1888-1971; Franck, James, 1882-1964.; Frankenburger, L.; Franz, E.; Fromherz, Hans, 1902-; Haber, Fritz, 1868-1934.; Hantzsch, A.; Hassel, Odd, 1897-1981; Herzberg, Gerhard, 1904-1999; Hevesy, Georg von, 1885-1966.; Honigschmid, Otto.; Kasha, Michael, 1920-; Kolthoff, I. M. (Izaak Maurits), 1894-1993; Kuhn, Richard, 1900-1967.; Lange, Erich, 1896-; Laue, Max von, 1879-1960.; Lembert, Max E. (Max Ernest), d. 1925.; Meitner, Lise, 1878-1968.; Nernst, Walter, 1864-1941.; Niggli, Paul, 1888-1953.; Ostwald, Wilhelm, 1853-1932.; Paneth, Fritz, 1887-1958.; Pauli, Wolfgang, 1900-1958.; Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994; Richards, Theodore W. (Theodore William), 1868-1928.; Rossini, Frederick D. (Frederick Dominic), 1899-; Rutherford, Ernest, 1871-1937.; Seaborg, Glenn T. (Glenn Theodore), 1912-1999; Soddy, Frederick, 1877-1956.; Sommerfeld, Arnold, 1868-1951.; Standinger, Hermann, 1881-1965.; Szwarc, Michael M., 1909-; Taylor, Hugh Scott, 1890-; Urey, Harold Clayton, 1893-1981.; Van Artsdalen, Ervin R.; Walden, Paul, 1863-1957.; Weyl, Woldemar A. (Woldemar Anatol), 1901-; Wieland, Heinrich, 1877-1957.; Willstðatter, Richard, 1872-1942.; Wycoff, Ralph W. G. (Ralph Walter Graystone), 1897-; Zeeman, Pieter, 1865-1943.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  Correspondence is the largest series in the collection and consists of two subseries, files arranged alphabetically and files arranged by subject or other grouping. As a gifted teacher and supportive colleague, Fajans corresponded with friends, students, and fellow scientists. His correspondents include numerous Nobel laureates, e.g. Otto Hahn, George Hevesy, Ernest Rutherford, Glenn Seaborg, and Richard Willstatter. The correspondence is substantial, with discussions of scientific theories, and the exchanging of interpretations and experimental results. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and is strongest for the period since his immigration to the United States. Perhaps one-third of the correspondence is in German.
  - Alphabetical
    - Unidentified (Box 1)
    - [A] (Box 1)
    - Anders, Oswald (Box 1)
    - Antonoff, George (Box 1)
    - Arndt, Fritz (Box 1)
    - [B], 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Badash, Lawrence 1963-1975, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Barber, S.W. (Box 1)
    - Barker, E.F. (Box 1)
    - Botsanov, S.S. (Box 1)
    - Bauer, Norman 1945-1962, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Bent, Henry A. (Box 1)
    - Bentur, S. (Box 1)
    - Berlin, Theodore H. September 1944-1963, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Born, Max (Box 1)
    - Böttcher, C.J.F., 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Bredig, Georg (Box 1)
    - Bredig, Max 1937-1974, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Brucer, Marshall (Box 2)
    - [C] (Box 2)
    - Cade, P.E. (Box 2)
    - Chaltykian, O. (Box 2)
    - Chardonnens, Louis (Box 2)
    - Cherbuliez, E. (Box 2)
    - Cohen, Howard (Box 2)
    - Conant, James. (Box 2)
    - Corwin, Alsoph H. (Box 2)
    - Coulson, C.S. (Box 2)
    - Curet, Juan (Box 2)
    - [D] (Box 2)
    - Delgarno, Alexander (Box 2)
    - Deno, N.C. (Box 2)
    - DeRocco, Andrew (Box 2)
    - Dolejsek, V. (Box 2)
    - Dreisbach, Robert (Box 2)
    - [E] (Box 2)
    - Eggert, John (Box 2)
    - Einstein, Albert (Box 2)
    - Evald, Paul (Box 2)
    - [F] (Box 2)
    - Frank, I.M. (Box 2)
    - Fujimoto, George, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Fumi, Fausto (Box 2)
    - [G] (Box 2)
    - Grosse, A.V. (Box 2)
    - Glasstone, Samuel (Box 2)
    - [H] (Box 2)
    - Hahn, Otto (Box 2)
    - Hass, Marvin (Box 2)
    - Herzberg, Gerhard (Box 2)
    - Hevesy, George 1912-1919 (Box 2)
      (contains letters to Ernest Rutherford)
    - Hevesy, George 1921-1965 (Box 2)
    - Hildebrand, Joel (Box 2)
    - Hillig, William and Beth 1946-1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Honigschmid, Otto (Box 3)
    - Hoseman, R. (Box 3)
    - Hückel, Walter (Box 3)
    - Hunt, John P. (Box 3)
    - Hyde, Earl K. (Box 3)
    - Ihde, Aaron J. (Box 3)
    - Ioffe (Box 3)
    - [J] (Box 3)
    - Johnson, Oliver 1945-1974, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Jørgensen, Christian Khebrill (Box 3)
    - [K] (Box 3)
    - Karreman, George, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Kasha, Michael (Box 3)
    - King, John Fitch (Box 3)
    - Kirby, Harold W. (Box 3)
    - Koenig, Marie L (Box 3)
    - Kolthoff', I.M., 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Krivomasov, A.N., 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Kurtz, S.S. (Box 3)
    - [L], 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Lange, Erich (Box 3)
    - Laue, M. (Box 3)
    - Lembert, Max (Box 3)
    - Lewin, Seymour (Box 3)
    - Lih, Kun-Hou. (Box 3)
    - Lühdemann, Rolf (Box 3)
    - [M] (Box 3)
    - Majumdar, Subodh Kumar (Box 3)
    - Manalo, Gloria D. (Box 3)
    - Mathias, Simâo (Box 4)
    - Meitner, Lise (Box 4)
    - Meyer, Lothar (Box 4)
    - Michael, Miriam. (Box 4)
    - Morris, Donald 1955-1973, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - [N] (Box 4)
    - [O] (Box 4)
    - [P], 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Paneth, Fritz (Box 4)
    - Parson, A.L. (Box 4)
    - Pauling, Linus (Box 4)
    - Penneman, Robert A. (Box 4)
    - [R] (Box 4)
    - Redlich, Otto (Box 4)
    - Ressler, Newton, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Rice, Oscar K. (Box 4)
    - Richards, T.W. (Box 4)
    - Rittner, Edmund S. (Box 4)
    - Rona, Elizabeth (Box 4)
    - Rossini, Frederick D. (Box 4)
    - Rundle, R.E. (Box 4)
    - Rutherford, Ernest (Box 4)
    - Ryshkewitch, Eugene (Box 4)
    - [S], 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Samuel, R. (Box 4)
    - Seaborg, Glenn (Box 4)
    - Shaw, Robert (Box 4)
    - Sidgewick, Nevil (Box 4)
    - Sommerfeld, Arnold (Box 4)
    - Stevels, J.M. (Box 4)
    - Sullivan, William H. (Box 4)
    - Szwarc, Michael (Box 4)
    - [T] (Box 5)
    - Taylor, Hugh (Box 5)
    - [U-V] (Box 5)
    - Urey, Harold C. (Box 5)
    - Ursprung, A. (Box 5)
    - VanArtsdalen, Ervin, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - [W], 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Weidenborner, James (Box 5)
    - Weiss, Francis (Box 5)
    - Weyl, W.A. 1943-1969, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Wheland, G.W. (Box 5)
    - Wieland, H. (Box 5)
    - Wilds, Alfred (Box 5)
      (mostly about the Gould Review)
    - Wilson, Norton (Box 5)
    - Willstatter, Richard (Box 5)
    - Wizinger, R. (Box 5)
    - Wright, George F. (Box 5)
    - [Z] (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Congratulatory letters upon occasion of his retirement May 1956 (Box 5)
    - Congratulations on the occasion of Kasimir Fajans Day in Ann Arbor, Mich. May 27, 1974. (Box 5)
    - Letters from Students and Colleagues from Munich and Karlsruhe (Box 5)
    - Letters from Students at University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, 2 folders (Box 5)
      (arranged alphabetically)
    - Helfman Scholarships 1940 (Box 5)
      (financial aid for European Scholars)
    - Einstein, Albert and Fajans, Kasimir on immigration of Helmut Blume to Canada 1942, photocopies (Box 5)
    - Correspondence with USSR Embassy in Washington and with Professors Kedrov, Frankel, Skriabin, and Staroselskia-Nikitina of the Soviet Union 1970-1974 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence re United States lectures 1928-1930 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence with Polish scholars, 1 folders; photocopies (Box 5)
      (in Polish)
- Lectures and symposia
  The Lectures and symposia series includes information about lectures given by Fajans. Most of this material comes from the period when Fajans had immigrated to the United States in the mid-1930s.
  - Lecture notes 1930-1966, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Papers related to lectures
    - 1918-1930 (Box 6)
    - 1931-1950 (Box 6)
    - 1951-1955 (Box 6)
      (primarily Oak Ridge, Tennessee; Europe)
    - 1956-1960 (Box 6)
    - 1961-1965 (Box 6)
  - Geneva Symposium materials 1965, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Hahn lecture materials 1966 (Box 6)
  - Marie Sklodowska-Curie Centenary Celebration materials 1967 (Box 6)
  - USSR National Academy of Sciences 250th anniversary celebration materials 1974 (Box 6)
  - Engineering Society at Detroit lecture materials 1975 (Box 6)
    (Kasimir Fajans was here awarded the Society's Gold Award)
  - Circular letter about CERI Symposium on hard and soft acids 1965 (Box 6)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files, also consisting mainly of correspondence, includes files on Fajans' research and professional interests and activities.
  - Adsorption indicators (experiments on) (Box 6)
  - Berlin, Theodore H., 9 folders (Box 6)
    (includes material related to collaboration with Kasimir Fajans; mostly computations)
  - Berlin, Theodore. Electronic Structure (draft) (Box 6)
  - Bonding and valence (notes and computations), 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Boron compounds (correspondence about with diagrams) (Box 6)
  - Brevium, correspondence relating to the naming of (Box 6)
  - "The Born-Einstein letters" (Box 6)
    (remarks about Fajans, translation error)
  - Chemistry 188, student comments (Box 6)
  - Chemistry courses--test and problems (Box 6)
  - Computations (Box 7)
  - Computations (Titration), 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Computations (Heat capacity) (Box 7)
  - Curie, Marie (Box 7)
    (with article written by Fajans)
  - Dipole polarization article by J.N. Wilson and R.M. Curtis 1968 (Box 7)
    (Fajans remarks on introduction)
  - "Fajans' Rules" (Box 7)
    (correspondence with authors of chemistry textbooks about their treatment of)
  - Farnsworth (Marie), manuscripts and charts (Box 7)
  - Kirby (H.W.), The Early History of Radiochemistry (Box 7)
  - Linton (E.P.), Report to Fellowship Board of the Royal Society (Box 7)
  - Manhattan Project (correspondence about) 1942 (Box 7)
  - Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company 1952-1971, 3 folders (Box 7)
    (correspondence with, mostly Ray Holmen)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    (in German)
  - Miscellaneous (unprocessed), 1 folders (Box 7)
  - Moseley (H.G.J.). Correspondence relating to biography of (Box 7)
  - Nobel Prize (requests for possible candidates from Fajans) (Box 7)
  - Owens-Illinois correspondence 1949 (Box 7)
  - Protactinium
    - Correspondence relating to the chemistry of protactinium and the International Protactinium Conference (Box 7)
    - International Protactinium Conference, Mittelwald, Germany April 1969 (Box 7)
  - Quanticule Theory
    - Correspondence relating to the quanticule theory 1944-1952 (Box 7)
    - Student paper on the quanticule theory (Box 7)
  - Radioactivity (history of and related), 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Radio akivitat (Reviews and translations of) 1932-1936 (Box 8)
  - Resonance Theory. Application of the Resonance Theory to the Structure of the Water Molecule (Box 8)
  - Russian Scientific literature (correspondence about the possibility of Fajans translating) (Box 8)
  - Sabbatical, Papers detailing activities of 1948 (Box 8)
  - Schmid (Gerhard), "Löslichkeitsuntersuchungen an halogenbenzoesauren Silber-und Thalliumsalzent" (Box 8)
  - Shell Development Company Seminar October 10, 1953 (Box 8)
  - Shell Development Company correspondence 1954-1960 (Box 8)
  - Sigma Xi, re possible publication of the article "New Confirmations of the Quanticule Theory" (Box 8)
  - Smithsonian Institution, re possibility of donating some memorabilia to commemorate his work (Box 8)
  - Society for the Protection of Science correspondence 1971 (Box 8)
  - Student papers, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Thorium Lead, Correspondence relating to 1938-1950 (Box 8)
  - Wilstatter (Richard), correspondence relating to biography of (Box 8)
- Publications
  The Publications series includes both published and unpublished materials. The first subseries, which relates to the publishing of his books and articles, includes correspondence with editors and referees. These exchanges are revealing not only of the intellectual and experimental aspects of the research, but also of the sociology of scientific investigation and publishing. The correspondence with scientists and publishers is particularly strong on Fajans' quanticule theory of chemical binding, which he considered equal in importance with his work on radioactivity. Other portions of this series consist of reprints of Fajans and others, books authored by Fajans, and a set of the German doctoral dissertations prepared under Fajans' tutelage.
  - Pertaining to publications
    - Correspondence with editors 1919-1973
      - 1919-1922 (Box 8)
      - 1941-1945 (Box 8)
      - 1946-1956 (Box 8)
      - 1960-1965 (Box 8)
      - 1966-1970 (Box 8)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence with Journal of the American Chemical Society 1950-1960 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence related to 3rd edition Technique of Organic Chemistry, October 1955-May 1960, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Correspondence related to 4th edition Technique of Organic Chemistry, 1965-1968, 1969-1972, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Correspondence related to "Polarization" article in Encyclopedia of Chemistry 1955-1957 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence relating to publication of "Quanticule Theory of Chemical Bonding" in CHIMIA 1958-1960 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence related to defense of views on coordination compounds 1959 (Box 8)
      (in response to article written by George E. Kimball and E.M. Loebl)
    - Correspondence with Interscience, 1958-1968 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence concerning review of Gould's Inorganic Reactions and Structures, 1962-1964 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence related to various directories and handbooks 1964-1974 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence relating to publication of "Degrees of Polarity and Mutual Polarization of ions in the molecules of Alkali Fluorides, SrO and BaO," in Journal of Chemical Physics, 1966-1970 (Box 8)
    - Articles, reviews, and papers 1913-1971, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Articles, reviews, papers, and drafts undated, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - History of Binding Theories (draft), 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Chemical Binding, chapter four (drafts and computations) (Box 9)
    - Refractometry (draft) by Norman Bauer, K. Fajans, and S.Z. Levin (Box 9)
    - Electronic Structure of Molecules and an introductory lecture, "The Development of Views Regarding the Nature of Chemical Forces" (Box 9)
    - Articles co-authored by Chien-HoLn Chu and Kasimir Fajans (Box 9)
    - "Applications of the Quanticule Theory to Biochemistry"; "Special Configurations and Interatomic Binding" (drafts) (Box 9)
    - Two articles on properties and structure of vitreous, liquid, and crystalline boron oxide by S.W. Barber and K. Fajans (Box 9)
    - Pankhurst, "N02+,NO2, and N02-"; Sisler et al General Chemistry (drafts of reviews) (Box 9)
    - "New confirmations of the Quanticule Theory" (Box 9)
  - Reprints of Fajans
    - 1908-1912 (Box 9)
    - 1913-1914, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1915-1916 (Box 9)
    - 1917-1919 (Box 9)
    - 1920-1923, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1924-1928, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1929-1932 (Box 10)
    - 1933-1937, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1938-1945, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1946-1950, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1951-1960, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1961- (Box 10)
  - Reprints of others
    - 1908-1913, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1914-1915 (Box 10)
    - 1916-1925 (Box 10)
    - 1926-1928 (Box 10)
    - 1929-1930, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1931-1932, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1933-1934, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1935-1937 (Box 10)
    - 1938-1949 (Box 10)
    - 1950-1970 (Box 10)
  - Signed Reprints
    - Reprint signed by Pauling (Box 10)
    - Reprints signed by Rutherford, 3 folders (Box 11)
      (Not inventoried)
  - Books by Fajans
    - Not inventoried (Box 11)
    - Not inventoried (Box 12)
      (continued)
  - Dissertations, etc.
    - Reviews of doctoral dissertations performed in Kasimir Fajans' laboratory, Germany (Box 13)
    - German Dissertations, 1 folders; 24 volumes (Box 13)
- Biographical/Personal material
  The Biographical/personal series consists of collected information about Fajans, the awards he received during his lifetime, papers belonging to Mrs. Fajans, and the correspondence surrounding his invitation to come to the University of Freiburg and the University of Michigan.
  - Biographical information (Box 14)
    (includes data on publications, students, and career)
  - Personal documents of Kasimir and Salomea Fajans (Box 14)
    (includes birth and marriage certificates and diplomas)
  - Bibliographies (Box 14)
  - Biographical articles (Box 14)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 14)
  - Invitation to the Professorship at University of Freiburg (Box 14)
  - Invitation to the Professorship at the University of Michigan. (Box 14)
  - Kasimir Fajans Award, University of Michigan, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Citations and honorary memberships (Box 14)
    (also in oversize folder, Ac)
  - Student Evaluations (Box 14)
  - Condolence letters to Mrs. Fajans upon death of Fajans 1975, 5 folders (Box 14)
  - Correspondence between Aleksander Nikolaievitch re: Fajans biography 1977-1980 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence of Mrs. Fajans re: Fajans' papers 1978-1981 (Box 14)
  - American Chemical Society Symposium in Commemoration of the Centennial of Fajans' birth 1987 (Box 14)
  - "Vom Atom Zum Weltgefuge," by Rudolph Heinrich, 3 volumes (Box 14)
    (dissertation that refers to the work and correspondence of Fajans, H.G. Grimm and others)
  - Kasimir Fajans, Lebenbild eines Wissenschaftlers" 2000 (Box 14)
    (Biography by Jozef Hurwig translated into German (from Polish) by Edgar Swinn. Also includes correspondence between Swinn and Stefan S. Fajans)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists of ten folders and three albums. This series includes portraits of Fajans alone, with his family, colleagues, and students, and in his laboratory. One album also consists of photos of the construction at the Institute of Physical Chemistry, University of Munich.
  - Portraits of Fajans (Box 14)
  - Fajans with his family (Box 14)
  - University of Munich and Manchester University (Box 14)
  - Fajans and colleagues (Box 14)
  - Fajans and students (Box 14)
  - Portraits of colleagues and other scientists: Richard Willstatter, Otto Hahn, Marie Curie, etc. (Box 14)
  - Picture from Curie Congress 1967 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Picture from the Academy of Sciences 200th Anniversary meeting, Leningrad 1925 (Box 14)
  - Pictures from Institute for Radiochemistry, Terhninhen Universital 1973 (Box 14)
  - Album containing portraits of Fajans alone, with colleagues, and students, in his laboratory, and of construction at the Institute of Physical Chemistry, University of Munich circa 1932 (Box 14)
  - Album containing portraits of colleagues and other scientists, as well as Fajans alone and with colleagues 1913-1960 (Box 15)
  - Album containing photographs of Fajans and colleagues at the Symposium to Celebrate the Anniversary of the Birth of Madame Curie, Warsaw 1967 (Box 15)